<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to a late pamphlet intituled, The judgement and doctrine of the clergy of the Church of England concerning one special branch of the King's prerogative, viz, in dispensing with the penal-laws shewing that this is not affected by the Most Reverend Fathers in God, the Lords Arch-Bishops, Bancroft, Laud and Usher ... the Lord Bishop Sanderson ... the Reverend Doctors, Dr. Hevlin, Dr. Barrow, Dr. Sherlock ... Dr. Hicks, Dr. Nalson, Dr. Puller, so far as appears from their words cited in this pamphlet : in a letter to a friend.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11925498</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11925498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51008</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25519)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51008)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to a late pamphlet intituled, The judgement and doctrine of the clergy of the Church of England concerning one special branch of the King's prerogative, viz, in dispensing with the penal-laws shewing that this is not affected by the Most Reverend Fathers in God, the Lords Arch-Bishops, Bancroft, Laud and Usher ... the Lord Bishop Sanderson ... the Reverend Doctors, Dr. Hevlin, Dr. Barrow, Dr. Sherlock ... Dr. Hicks, Dr. Nalson, Dr. Puller, so far as appears from their words cited in this pamphlet : in a letter to a friend.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 39 [i.e. 37] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Prerogative, Royal --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England --  History --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51008:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51008:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER to a late PAMPHLET, INTITULED, <hi rend="blackletterType">The Iudgment and Doctrine of the Clergy</hi> OF THE CHURCH of ENGLAND, Concerning one Special Branch of the KING's PREROGATIVE; <hi>VIZ.</hi> 
               <hi rend="blackletterType">In diſpenſing with the Penal-Laws.</hi> SHEWING That this is not aſſerted by
<list>
                  <item>The Moſt Reverend Fathers in God, the Lords Arch-Biſhops, <hi>Bancroft, Laud</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Right Reverend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Reverend Doctors, Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> Maſter of the <hi>Temple,</hi> Dr. <hi>Hicks,</hi> Dr. <hi>Nalſon,</hi> Dr. <hi>Puller,</hi> So far as appears from their words cited in THIS PAMPHLET.</item>
               </list> In a LETTER to a Friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard.</hi> MDCLXXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:51008:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May 13. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IL. NEEDHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51008:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to a late Pamphlet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have received the Book you ſent me, Intituled, [<hi>The Judgment and Doctrine of the Clergy of the Church of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>concerning one ſpecial branch of the King's Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> viz. <hi>Diſpenſing with the Penal Laws.</hi>] Had I not now learnt to wonder at nothing, it would a little have ſurprized me; but now I ſhall only tell you that I have read it, and do not like it: And reſerving one little reaſon for by and by, <hi>viz.</hi> That it is not true: I ſhall at preſent give you ſome other reaſons of my diſlike, to prevent miſtakes.</p>
            <p>And firſt negatively, Not becauſe it is for the King's diſpenſing Power; For I never envy my King any Prerogative that belongs to his Crown: And tho, it may be, this Branch of the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative was not ſo well underſtood in former days, yet it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly now the right of the Crown, as much as the Opinion of the Judges can make it ſo; and I never diſpute againſt ſuch an Authority: And I think it is a diſparagement to the judgment of the Reverend Judges to call in Clergy-men to help them out; when he himſelf tells us, p. 34. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Judges the people are bound laſtly and finally to ſubmit themſelves for matter of Law.</hi> Why then does he make any further diſpute about the matter? As if he diſtruſted the Judgment of the <hi>Judges,</hi> or thought that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would rather believe <hi>Divines</hi> than <hi>Judges</hi> in matter of Law; which would be a great ſcandal to that Reverend and Learned Bench. And therefore, I confeſs, I am very much offended with that priority he gives to the Judgment of <hi>Churchmen</hi> in this point, before the Judgment of the <hi>Judges.</hi> He ſays, <hi>We could not reſolve our ſelves in this great point (of the Supreme Power inherent in, and inſeparably annexed to the Crown, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with Penal Laws) but by theſe two ways.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:51008:3"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>To ſee, how far the Judgment of our Church-men, appearing in their Doctrines (which are for our edification) doth warrant this Prerogative to be in the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>To ſee how far the Judges Reſolutions (in declaring their ſence of the Law of the Land in this doubtful queſtion) do agree in ſuch their Judgments and Doctrines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fie for ſhame! Firſt, make the Clergy Judges of Law, and Preach <hi>edifyingly</hi> about the Prerogative, and then ſet them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Judges themſelves, as a Rule and Pattern for them to follow; and then, as it naturally follows, judg over the <hi>Judges</hi> judgment by its agreement with the judgment of <hi>Divines,</hi> about Law and Prerogative. If the Writer of this Letter was a <hi>Divine,</hi> it argues a good Opinion of his own Profeſſion; but if he were a Lawyer, or but a Juſtice of Peace, I know what he deſerves.</p>
            <p>Secondly, This brings me to the poſitive Reaſons of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like of this way, and they are comprehended in two: 1. That I do not think fit to lay ſuch ſtreſs upon the Judgment of <hi>Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> in matters of Law; and ſuch, ſure this unlimited diſpenſing Power is, a meer point of Law; and that ſuch an abſtruſe point too, as not all Lawyers, nay not all <hi>Judges</hi> have formerly been agreed about. Now, what does a <hi>Churchman's,</hi> Judgment ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify in matters of Law? No man's Opinion is of any value, but in ſuch things wherein he is skilled; now a Churchman does not ſignifie one, who is skilled in Law, but in Divinity: And tho a Church-man ſhould be a good Lawyer; if he gives his Opinion in any point of Law, his Opinion is not valuable, as the Opinion of a Church-man, but of a Lawyer; for ſuppoſe a Church-man were skilled in Phyſick too, would you value his Judgment in Phyſick ever the more, becauſe he is a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? Or think your ſelf more ſafe in his hands, than in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Phyſicians? There are Interlopers indeed in all Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but that any man's Judgment ſhould be valued, becauſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one Profeſſion himſelf, he gives judgment in another, is a Myſtery to me. And therefore this Writer ſhould firſt have proved all thoſe great Divines, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deans,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51008:3"/> Doctors, with whoſe names he hath ſo pompouſly filled his Title Page, and to whoſe judgment he appeals about the King's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, to haxe been great <hi>Lawyers,</hi> as well as great <hi>Divines,</hi> or elſe the Cauſe is <hi>Coram non judice;</hi> and yet he makes no offer at this, unleſs by the Title he gives Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> of <hi>Maſter of the Temple,</hi> he would intimate his great skill in <hi>Law</hi> too; but this will not do; for his Book of Non-reſiſtance was written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he liv'd within the infection of the Law-air. So that it ſeems a very great injury to the Cauſe to appeal to ſuch Judges as have no skill in the matter: For what credit can the Opinion of Divines do it, when it is not a point of Divinity, but of Law that is in queſtion? For it is generally ſeen, that thoſe are very apt to miſtake, who gueſs at things out of their Ken; and people are apt to ſuſpect that ſuch contemplative men, who keep their Studies, and ſeldom look abroad into the World, may form fine Romantick Idea's of Government, which will not ſuit the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Conſtitutions of Kingdoms and Nations.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I think it is a very dangerous thing to put the Queſtion upon ſuch an iſſue as this: The deſign of it, I ſuppoſe, is to recommend it to the Layety of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by ſuch venerable Names; but he ſhould have conſidered, that the Layety of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not ſo Prieſt-ridden, as they are at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Geneva;</hi> they have not an implicite Faith in their ſpiritual Guides, and their Guides do not deſire they ſhould; and therefore it is not their Names but their Arguments muſt prevail; but if people are taught to rely on the opinion of their Miniſters in ſuch Prerogative Diſputes, the <hi>Popiſh Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Phanatick Miniſters</hi> are great Politicians too; but if they may be Judges, Sovereign Princes will get nothing by it. The Church of <hi>England</hi> indeed has always been addicted to the Service of the Crown, but there are other Maxims of Government among other men: <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Suarez,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and the Diſſenters Sayings, not to take notice now of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, are not very favourable to the Prerogatives of Princes; and I fear people are more inclinable to follow ſuch
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51008:4"/> Guides as theſe, and therefore I ſhould have thought it more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſable to have taught people more to rely on the Opinions of <hi>Judges</hi> than of <hi>Divines,</hi> in matters of Prerogative and Law; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I fear that the honeſt <hi>Prerogative Divines</hi> will be greatly out-numbred by the <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Phanatick Common-wealths<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men;</hi> and whether this will prove for the ſervice of the King, ſhould have been conſidered.</p>
            <p n="2">2. My ſecond Reaſon, why I diſlike this way is, That I fear inſtead of doing ſervice, it will do great diſſervice to the <hi>King,</hi> by weakning the Authority of thoſe many excellent diſcourſes, which have been written about Non-reſiſtance, and which did great ſervice, not only to former Kings, but even to our <hi>preſent Soveraign</hi> in the late evil and critical times. It will not eaſily be forgot how many hard Cenſures thoſe honeſt Divines underwent, who durſt both from the Pulpit and the Preſs oppoſe that factious humour which was then ſo rampant, and preſaged thoſe wicked Conſpiracies, which were afterwards by the Divine Providence ſo happily diſcovered and diſappointed. The Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance would very hardly go down, and the great objection againſt it was, That it made the Prince abſolute, and ſet him above all Laws, which were Laws no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger than he pleaſed to have them ſo; and thus our Lives and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, and Liberties and Religion, were at the Will of the Prince; and if this were really the natural conſequence of the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, I ſuſpect it would to this day put a great many Engliſh Subjects out of conceit with it; and yet this is in great meaſure the deſign of this Letter, to apply thoſe Sayings or Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, which were urged for the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, to prove a Diſpenſing Power inherent and inſeparable from the Crown. Now far be it from me to diſpute this Point, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be ſuch an inherent Right in the Crown or no, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as far as the <hi>Judges</hi> have determined that there is; but this I ſay, That it is not a neceſſary Conſequence of the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance, that becauſe we muſt not reſiſt our Prince, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he does, therefore he may <hi>de jure</hi> diſpenſe with what Laws
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51008:4"/> he pleaſes; and I think it is for the Intereſt of the Crown, that theſe <hi>two</hi> ſhould be kept diſtinct; that the Prerogatives of the Crown ſhould be aſſerted and maintained upon their own bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; and that the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance (which muſt defend all other Prerogatives, and is a better and cheaper ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than Forts and Caſtles) may not be entangled with other Diſputes, which will weaken its Authority, though it be Divine, when it is clogged, as ſome men will think, with ſuch uneaſie and fatal conſequences. This, I confeſs gives me a juſt indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt thoſe half-witted Scriblers, who to ſerve, as they think, a preſent turn, have endeavoured to leſſen the Reputation, and to weaken the Arguments of thoſe Divines, who have appeared ſo zealous for the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance and Paſſive Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, by affixing a great many conſequences to them, which are neither conſequences, nor theirs; and by wreſting their words to other purpoſes, than they intended; and for this reaſon I judg it a very good piece of Service to the Crown to undertake the Vindication of the men, and of their Doctrines.</p>
            <p>For Divines to determine points of Law, eſpecially ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire deep skill and inſight into the nature of the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as I obſerved before, is out of their Sphere; but obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Soveraign Princes, both Active and Paſſive, is not mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a point of Law, but a Goſpel command, and this they not only may, but ought to explain and preſs upon the Conſciences of their hearers: This the Church of <hi>England</hi> her ſelf has done in the Homily of Obedience, and this the Miniſters of the Church have taken all occaſions to do, and with that ſucceſs, that there are not more Loyal Subjects in the World, than the true Sons of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but farther than this, they have not gone, or if a few dablers in Politicks have, let them anſwer for themſelves: The Scripture teaches Obedience, but the Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of Princes, and the Liberties of Subjects, are the matter of human Laws and Conſtitutions, which properly belong to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gown.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:51008:5"/>
            <p>And thus I come to conſider what Teſtimonies this Writer has produced to prove, That it is the Doctrine and Judgment of the Reverend Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Power of Diſpenſing with any Laws is an inherent and inſeparable Right of the Crown; where I will not meddle with the main point, Whether the King have any ſuch right (for I will not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute that) but whether theſe Divines, whoſe Authority is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in the cauſe, ever taught any ſuch Doctrine. He begins with the Reverend Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> Dean of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> and endeavours to render one of the beſt Books that ever was wrote for Paſſive Obedience, wholly uſeleſs or odious to thoſe men who are not fond of the diſpenſing Power. But what does the Dean teach? <hi>That the Engliſh Realm is a perfect Soveraignty or Empire, and that the King of England by the Imperial Laws of it, is a Compleat, Imperial, Independent Soveraign; that it is a contradiction to call this an Imperial Crown — unleſs he have all thoſe Rights, which are involved in the very Notion of his Imperial Soveraignty.</hi> Well! to make ſhort work with it, does the Dean ſay, That this Diſpenſing Power is one of thoſe Rights which are involved in the notion of Imperial Soveraignty? No, he ſays no ſuch thing; but this Writer ſays ſo for him, that <hi>this Power of diſpenſing with Penal Laws muſt be, or nothing, one of thoſe Prerogatives;</hi> which he proves from Sir <hi>Robert Pointz</hi> his Vindication of Monarchy; and what then? ſuppoſe it be, does the Dean ſay ſo? for that is the only point in queſtion, What his Judgment is?</p>
            <p>No, but he ſays, That the Imperial Crown has all the Rights which are involved in the Notion of Imperial Soveraignty, and our Author can prove, that the diſpenſing Power is ſuch a Right, and therefore the Dean muſt grant, that this diſpenſing Power is a Right inherent in the Crown. Very well! A Popiſh Prieſt will allow, that an Imperial Crown has all the Rights that are involved in the Notion of Imperial Soveraignty; now ſay I, a Supremacy in all Cauſes, over all Perſons, as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil, is an inherent Authority of the Imperial Crown; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Popiſh Prieſts renounce the Supremacy of the Biſhop of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51008:5"/> 
               <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>me,</hi> and own the Supremacy of the Kings of <hi>England.</hi> If he think this is not a good proof, let him conſider this matter over again, which will be worth the while, if it be only to teach him to Reaſon a little. When there is any Diſpute about the rights of Soveraignty, it is a ridiculous inference to ſay, That he who owns all the Rights of Soveraignty, owns whatever any man ſays is a Right of Soveraignty; for ſtill he owns no more, than what he himſelf believes to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Now I am not concern'd to enquire what Dr. <hi>Hicks</hi> believes about the Diſpenſing Power, but what he has ſaid; and our Author has not produced one word out of his Book about it; and therefore I ſuppoſe he could not; for his own words had been a better Authority in this caſe than Sir <hi>Robert Pointz:</hi> I am ſure, where he particularly ſtates and enumerates the Rights of Soveraignty, he takes no notice of it; for as he reckons them up, they are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jovian, or an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Julian the Apoſtate, chap. 10. p. 201. Ed. 1.</note> 1. <hi>To be <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, accountable to none except God.</hi> 2. <hi>To have the ſole Power and diſpoſal of the Sword.</hi> 3. <hi>To be free from all Coercive and vindicative Power.</hi> 4. <hi>Not to be withſtood or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by force, upon any pretence whatſoever. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. To have the Legiſlative Power, that makes any form of words a Law: The Soveraign Power may indeed be limited as to the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of this Power, which may be confined to Bills and Writings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared by others; but ſtill it is the Soveraign Authority, who gives Life and Soul to the dead Letter of them.</hi> Here is nothing at all about this Diſpenſing Power, when there was a fair occaſion for it: Poſſibly this was an Omiſſion, which at that time he did not think of, that not being the matter of Diſpute; or it may be he was not ſo well inſtructed, and did not think this eſſential to the notion of all Soveraign Power, as ſeems probable from his <hi>two ſorts of Imperial Power,</hi> either of which <hi>make an Imperial Soveraign; ſuch as is limited by the Laws of God and nature only; or ſuch as is limited by the Laws of God and nature, and Civil Laws and Pactions too; The Power in both ſorts of Soveraigns is Imperial, full, perfect, abſolute and entire; but the exerciſe of it is different<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51008:6"/> bounded and regulated; one by the Laws of God and Nature, and the other by human poſitive Laws; and the latter limitation, doth no more deſtroy the fulneſs and perfection and Supremacy of the Power, than the former; becauſe the Soveraign, who is under Political li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitations, as to the exerciſe of his Power, hath his Power never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs as abſolutely, fully and entirely in himſelf, as he that is only under the limitation of Divine and natural Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">De laudibus legum An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae C. 9. Rex Angliae — principatu nedum Regali ſed Politico ſuo populo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatur. Regnum ſic inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tui, ut Rex non libere valeat populum tyrannide guber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare, quod ſolum fit dum poteſtas regia lege politica cohibetur.</note> 
               <hi>Thus the learned Chancellor Forteſcue grants the King of England to have Regal or Imperial Power, though it be under the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint and regulation of the Power political, as to the exerciſe thereof; and as a Fountain that hath Channels and Pipes made for it, within which its waters are bounded in their paſſage, and through which they are to flow, is nevertheleſs as perfect a Fountain, and hath its waters as fully and entirely within it ſelf, as any other Fountain, whoſe waters flow from it at liberty, without any ſuch regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; ſo a King whoſe Imperial Power is limited by human Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions in the exerciſe of it, is nevertheleſs as compleat a Soveraign, and hath the Soveraign Power as fully and entirely within himſelf, as he who is at liberty to exerciſe his Authority as he will: To be arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is no more of the Eſſence of an Imperial Soveraign, than to be free in the courſe of its waters is of the Eſſence of a Fountain; but as the Fountain of an Aqueduct, for example, is as perfect, in its kind, and generally more beneficial and uſeful to mankind, than a free flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpring; ſo limited Soveraigns are as perfect and eſſential Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, as the purely arbitrary and deſpotick, and generally more beneficial and ſalutary to the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A great deal more the Reader may find to this purpoſe in the ſame place, which poſſibly may be the reaſon, why he did not mention this abſolute Diſpenſing Power among the Eſſential Rights of Soveraignty; becauſe he might imagine, that this might not be eſſential to all Soveraigns; not to thoſe, the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of whoſe Soveraign Power is regulated by Civil and Political
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51008:6"/> Laws, who yet are as perfect Soveraigns, as the moſt arbitrary and deſpotick Princes. But I do not love to gueſs at other mens thoughts, nor ſhall I undertake to juſtifie or condemn this Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his; but I think, the Reader by this time ſees what little reaſon there was to appeal to the Dean of <hi>Worceſter</hi> to juſtifie the diſpenſing Power.</p>
            <p>His next Authority is Arch-biſhop <hi>Bancroft,</hi> who it ſeems aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, <hi>That the Judges are but the Kings Delegates, and that the King may take what cauſes he ſhall pleaſe to determine, from the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of the Judges, and determine them himſelf, which the Archbiſhop ſaid was clear in Divinity, that ſuch Authority belongs to the King by the Word of God in Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I wonder this Writer would produce this, and that for theſe two Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe at that very time in the Preſence of King <hi>James,</hi> my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Coke</hi> contradicted the Arch-biſhop, and told the King he could not do it, and gave him his Reaſons why he could not, as the Ch. Juſtice him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reports it, in that place to which this Writer refers.<note place="margin">12 <hi>Co. Fol.</hi> 64. 5. Jac.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now methinks here he loſes more than he gets; for if he have got a great Church-man, he has loſt a very great Lawyer, whoſe Judgment is more conſiderable in ſuch matters; for as the Arch-Biſhop could tell him what hath been done in Scripture-times under the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Common-wealth, that <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon,</hi> and other Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> adminiſtred Juſtice in their own Perſons. So the Ch. Juſtice could tell him, what the Conſtitutions of this Kingdom, and the regular form of Law will admit, which is more to our purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I wonder a little more, how he can prove the diſpenſing Power from this: The King may judg what cauſes he pleaſes himſelf. <hi>Ergo,</hi> He can diſpenſe with all Laws when he pleaſes. Does the Power of hearing and trying cauſes, and expounding, and interpreting Laws, include in it a power of diſpenſing with Laws? Then it ſeems every Judg is by his Office a Diſpenſer with Laws. If the King have Power of determining cauſes in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51008:7"/> his own perſon, muſt he judg with or without Law? If he judg according to the Laws, how does this prove his Power of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing with Laws? Surely this is a Power which can reſult only from a Supreme abſolute and unlimited Soveraignty, not from a mere power of hearing and judging cauſes, according to the true meaning and interpretation of Laws; ſo little does this Writer underſtand what he writes about; and it is great pity there is no more care taken that the Kings Prerogative do not ſuffer by ſuch unskilful Scriblers.</p>
            <p>His next man is a very great one indeed, not only an Archbiſhop, but a Martyr for his King and the Church; the famous Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> whoſe Judgment would weigh more with me, than ſome other mens Reaſons. He quotes a ſaying of his, out of his Book againſt <hi>Fiſher,</hi> but never directs us where to find it; and that is a great book to ſearch all over for one ſingle paſſage: but however the ſaying is ſo innocent, that we may admit it to be his, without farther Enquiry, <hi>viz. That the Supreme Magiſtrate in the Eſtate Civil, may not abrogate the Laws made in Parliament; tho he may diſpenſe with the Sanction or Penalty of the Law, quoad hic &amp; nunc, as the Lawyers ſpeak.</hi> Now unleſs <hi>quoad hic &amp; nunc</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a general and unlimited Diſpenſation for all perſons at all times, I ſuppoſe it does not reach the plenitude of the Diſpenſing Power. <hi>Quoad hic &amp; nunc,</hi> I doubt may be expounded as a limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Diſpenſing Power, which will beget a diſpute how far this Power of Diſpenſing may extend; for which reaſon I wiſh he had concealed the Judgment of this great Archbiſhop; tho the comfort is, he was but a Divine, and therefore his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment not Authentick in ſuch matters any farther than this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor has made it ſo, by appealing to it; eſpecially ſince he does not give his own Opinion in the caſe, but refers to the received opinion of Lawyers at that time, which whether it then was for an abſolute Diſpenſing Power, muſt be firſt known, before we can know what the Archbiſhops Opinion was.</p>
            <p>But he makes a much greater flouriſh with Archbiſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> who wrote an Excellent Book concerning <hi>the Power communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by God to the Prince, and the Obedience required of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject;</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51008:7"/> out of which he has tranſcribed four or five Pages, how much to his purpoſe, ſhall be preſently examined: But I muſt firſt mind him, what another of his Witneſſes, The Right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Dr. <hi>Sanderſon</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> has obſerved in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to that Book, Sect. 9, 12, 13. In the 9 Section he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of ſeveral Objections which either were or might be made againſt this Book. The Second is, <hi>That it is not yor Divines at all to meddle in theſe matters, whereof they are not competent Judges, nor do they come within the compaſs of their Sphere: They ought to be left to the cognizance and determination of States-men and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, who beſt underſtand the conſtitution of the ſeveral Governments, and the force and effect of the Laws of their own ſeveral reſpective Countries, and are therefore preſumed to be beſt able to judg, the one (by conſtitution) in whom the Soveraignty reſideth, and the other (by the Laws) how that Soveraignty is bounded and limited in the exerciſe thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this he ſays, Sect. 12. <hi>True it is, that for the more eaſe of the Governors, and better ſatisfaction of the people in ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their Properties, preſerving Peace amongſt them, and doing them Juſtice, the abſolute and unlimited Soveraignty, which Princes have by the Ordinance of God, hath at all times, and in all Nations, been diverſly limited and bounded in the ordinary exerciſe thereof by ſuch Laws and Cuſtoms as the Supreme Governors themſelves have conſented to and allowed. As with us in England, there are ſundry caſes, wherein a Subject, in maintenance of his Right and Property, may wage Law with the King, bring his Action, and have Judgment againſt him in open Court; and the Judges in ſuch caſes are bound by their Oaths and Duties to right the Party according to Law, againſt the King, as well as againſt the meaneſt of his Subjects.</hi> So that it ſeems, this Biſhop thought that the exerciſe of the Soveraignty might be limited by Laws, and by ſuch Laws as would hold good againſt the King himſelf in his own Courts, and therefore that all Laws were not diſpenſable at the Kings pleaſure; and this Preface was wrote long after his Caſes of Conſcience, of which more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently. And he adds, <hi>That the debating and determining of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubt or controverſie belongeth to the Learned Lawyers, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51008:8"/> Judges who are preſumed to be beſt skilled in the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Land, as their proper ſtudy, wherein they are daily converſant; and not to Divines, who (as Divines) are not competent Judges in theſe matters, nor do they come within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of their ſphere.</hi> By which one would gueſs that this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhop did not apprehend, that he himſelf had been guilty of determining ſo nice a Point of Law as <hi>the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing Power,</hi> tho this Author has diſcovered for him, that he has.</p>
            <p>Well, but how does he bring off the Arch-biſhop after all this, for medling with ſuch nice points? As to that he tells us, <hi>Sect.</hi> 13. That there is no need of bringing him off: That, <hi>in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the preſent Treatiſe,</hi> all that he had ſaid about Divines de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining Law Caſes, as far as they related to Conſcience, <hi>might well enough have been ſpared, wherein the Reverend Author, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out medling with theſe Punctilio's of the Law, undertaketh no more but to declare and aſſert the Power of Soveraign Princes, as the Godly Fathers and Councils of the ancient Catholick Church, from the evidence of Holy Scripture, and the moſt judicious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Writers by diſcourſe of Reaſon from the light of Nature, have conſtantly taught and acknowledged the ſame, as to the unprejudiced Reader by the peruſal of the Book it ſelf will eaſily appear.</hi> From whence one would gueſs, that Biſhop <hi>Saunderſon</hi> did not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, that Archbiſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> had determined any one point of Law, about the abſolute or limited exerciſe of the Soveraign Power, according to the Conſtitution of theſe Realms; and therein he had our Author differ, who has found the Diſpenſing Power plainly determined by the Archbiſhop. But whoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults the Book it ſelf (and it will reward any man's pains, who will do it) will find, that the Biſhop was in the right, and thoſe Reaſons which the Biſhop urges, will convince him, That he was ſo. For he will find, that the Archbiſhop does not meddle with the particular Laws and Conſtitutions of theſe Kingdoms, but only urges the Authority of Fathers and Councils, and the Holy Scriptures, and the conſent of Heathen Writers, which can no more determine what the particular Laws and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51008:8"/> of theſe Kingdoms are, than the Laws of <hi>England</hi> can the Cuſtoms of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire. The Archbiſhop only conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered what Rights belong to the Soveraign Power, wherever it is, by the conſent of Scriptures, Fathers, Councils and Heathen Writers, who followed the light and conduct of natural Reaſon; and took it for granted, as the Biſhop obſerves he well might, That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> are Soveraign Princes, and therefore have all the Rights of Soveraignty belonging to their Crowns: But how the exerciſe of this Soveraign Power is limited by the particular Laws and Cuſtoms of Nations, and by the conſent and grants of Soveraign Princes themſelves, which Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> aſſerts, <hi>has at all times, and in all Nations, been diverſly limited and bounded,</hi> this the Archbiſhop ſays nothing of; and I cannot then gueſs, how he ſhould determine this point of the <hi>Diſpenſing Power.</hi> But let us now conſider what this Author alledges to prove, That the Archbiſhop did teach, that this <hi>Diſpenſing Power</hi> is an inherent and inſeparable Right of the Imperial Crown: And to ſet this matter in a clearer light, I ſhall place his quotations in that natural Order they ſtand in in the Archbiſhops Book.</p>
            <p>He having then <hi>ſearched into the ground of Soveraignty, and (by Reaſon, and Witneſſes of all ſorts) deduced the Original thereof from no lower an head than Heaven it ſelf,</hi> as he himſelf tells us, <note place="margin">The Power of Princes. p. 66. <hi>Ed.</hi> 2. 1683.</note> he proceeds <hi>to look a little into thoſe Royal Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, which are annexed to the eminent Eſtate of ſuch ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governors.</hi> And the principal thing he takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, is their exemption from Laws; <note place="margin">P. 68.</note> as the Senate of <hi>Rome</hi> decreed to <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> That <hi>what Laws ſoever either of the Senate or People it was ordained, that the Emperor's Predeceſſors were not tied to, from thoſe he ſhould be looſe alſo:</hi> So that this freedom from Laws, tho a Branch of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Power, was decreed and confirmed by the Laws of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and granted to the Emperor by the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate; which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſignified making him Emperor, for without this he had not been an Imperial Prince.</p>
            <p>But what is this exemption from Laws which belongs to the Imperial Crown? And that he tells us from the Civilians, That
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51008:9"/> 
               <hi>they are free from all Coactive Obedience to them, and are held by none of the written Ordinances.</hi> For the underſtanding of which, he diſtinguiſhes between <hi>God's Law, the Law of the King, and that which is the Law of God and the King together.</hi> As for God's Law, which ſignifies the unwritten Law of Nature, or the Written Word, the greateſt Prince in the World is as much bound to obey it, as the meaneſt Subject. But then he adds, (which is one of our Author's quotations) <hi>By the Law of the King, I underſtand ſuch Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as are meerly Civil and Poſitive; the Coactive Power whereof being derived from him who is the ſupreme Law-giver under God on Earth, he himſelf cannot be properly ſaid to be tied thereby.</hi> Which he proves from Grammarians, Civilians, and Schoolmen, and by this good Argument. <hi>As no man therefore is ſuperior to himſelf, ſo no man hath juriſdiction over himſelf; becauſe none can oblige a man againſt his Will, but only his Superior; and the juriſdiction over a mans ſelf may be diſſolved at pleaſure.</hi> Which only ſignifies, that the King is not bound in his own perſon to obſerve the Laws as Subjects are, becauſe no body has any juriſdiction over him but himſelf, and no man can command himſelf any longer than he pleaſes. Right! But ſuppoſe a Soveraign Prince has bound himſelf by Oath to God and his Country, that he will obſerve the Laws, is he not as much obliged then to obſerve the Civil and Poſitive Laws of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, made and confirmed by his own Authority, as he is to obſerve the Laws of God? for tho by making a Law he does not immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately oblige himſelf, yet by his Oath he may. The Archbiſhop only conſidered what was the Right of Soveraign Power without any Super-induced obligation, not what a Soveraign Prince might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige himſelf to by Sacred and Solemn Oaths: And yet I wonder this Writer ſhould have no more regard to the Sacred Majeſty of Princes, than to found their Rights upon ſuch a Power, as the wiſeſt and beſt Princes have not thought fit to uſe: As he might have learnt in the ſame place had he thought fit to have read on. For there the Archbiſhop quotes the ſaying of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the younger. <note place="margin">p. 74.</note> 
               <hi>It is in truth a greater thing than the Empire, to ſubmit the Princed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m it ſelf unto the Laws.</hi> And that of <hi>Alexander Severus, Although the Law
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51008:9"/> of the Empire hath freed the Emperor from the Solemnities of the Law, yet nothing is ſo proper for Empire as to live by the Laws.</hi> And that which <hi>Severus</hi> and <hi>Antoninus</hi> ſet down ſo oft in their Preſcripts; <hi>Altho we be looſed from the Laws, yet we live by the Laws. Whereunto alſo we may add, that commendation which</hi> Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch <hi>giveth to</hi> Alexander <hi>the Great; That he conceived he ought to be thought Superior to all Men, yet ſubject to Juſtice;</hi> That is, to be obliged to obſerve all the Laws of Juſtice, not to be ſubiect to any Coercive Power. <hi>And</hi> Pliny to <hi>Trajan, He thinks himſelf to be one of us, and ſo much the more excellent and eminent he is, that he ſo thinketh; and no leſs remembreth that he is a Man, than that he is a Ruler of Men. For he who hath nothing left to increaſe his height, hath but this one way to grow by, if he ſubmit himſelf, being ſecure of his Greatneſs. And in his direct Speech to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror himſelf; Thou eſteemeſt us the ſame, and thy ſelf the ſame, and in this only greater than the reſt, that thou art better than they. And, Thou haſt made thy ſelf-ſubject to the Laws, O Caeſar, which were not written to reſtrain the Prince by; but Thou wilt have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more lawful to Thee, than is to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s.</hi> Now, when this has been the Senſe and Practice of the wiſeſt and beſt Heathen Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; that it is an Imperial Vertue and Dignity, tho they are free from Laws, yet to ſubmit themſelves to the obſervance of Laws: I ſhould think it no great Complement to a Chriſtian Prince to found any part of his Imperial Power upon ſuch Exemptions, as. Soveraign Power muſt have, but yet, which Soveraign Princes think it their greateſt Glory not to uſe: For if the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of ſuch a Liberty be inglorious; that Power, which is founded on it, cannot be glorious.</p>
            <p>And here comes in the firſt Citation of this Writer, who I think has not mended the Arch-Biſhop's Senſe by altering his Method. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Power of the Prince.</hi> P. 76.</note> 
               <hi>For ſuch poſitive Laws as theſe, being (as the other works of Men are) imperfect, and not free from many diſcommodities; if the ſtrict Obſervation thereof ſhould be peruſed in every particular, it is ſit the Supream Governour ſhould not himſelf only be excepted from ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51008:10"/> thereunto</hi> (which ſhows that before, he had only ſpoke of the perſonal exemption of the Prince from the neceſſity of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own Laws, and that he now enters upon a new Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative of the Crown in the Words that follow) <hi>but alſo be ſo far Lord over them, that where he ſeeth cauſe he may abate, or totally remit the Penalty incurred by the breach of them, diſpenſe with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers for not obſerving them at all, and generally ſuſpend the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them, when by experience he ſhall find the imconveniencies to be greater than the profit that was expected ſhould redound thereby to the Common-wealth.</hi> Plutarch <hi>ſctteth this down as a chief point of that natural skill, which</hi> Philopaemen <hi>had in Government, that he did not only rule according to the Laws, but over-ruled the Laws themſelves, when he found it conducing to the Weal-Publick.</hi> Now, I do not ſee one Word in this, but what is the undoubted Right of the Supream executive Power: For it is impoſſible any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould be well and happily governed, where this Power is not; And that for this Reaſon, which the Arch-Biſhop gives; Becauſe Human Laws are imperfect, and therefore there muſt be a living Authority to ſupply their Defects, and to temper their Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and to pity and relieve Subjects, when the caſe is truly pitiable. But then there are ſome natural Limitations of the exerciſe of this Power in the moſt abſolute and deſpotick Princes, and there may be Political Limitations of it by the conſent of Soveraign Princes themſelves, according to the Laws and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of ſeveral Kingdoms. For tho the Imperial Crown can be diveſted of no part of Soveraign Power, yet the exerciſe of it may be directed and limited by publick Laws, as we heard before from Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon.</hi> This laſt the Arch-Biſhop takes no notice of, it not being his deſign, as you heard before, to adjuſt the Rights of Princes by Political Laws, but only to conſider in general, what are the eſſential Rights of Soveraign Power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examining how the exerciſe of it is diverſly limited in diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Countries. And therefore let us only conſider what thoſe natural Bounds and Limits are, which he has ſet to this <hi>diſpenſing and ſuſpending Power.</hi> And they are included in the reaſon of this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51008:10"/> Power, becauſe all Human Laws are imperfect, and therefore there wants a Soveraign Power, which is ſo far Superior to all Laws, that it can correct their Faults, and ſupply their Defects, and temper them to ſuch particular Emergencies and Caſes, as could not be foreſeen when the Laws were made. For if human Laws could be ſo exactly framed, as to fit all poſſible caſes, if the Law were for the good of the Common-wealth, the <hi>diſpenſing</hi> with, or <hi>ſuſpending</hi> the execution of ſuch Laws, would be a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick miſchief: And a Power which could ſerve no good end, could be no Prerogative of Soveraignty. And therefore the very Diſpenſation muſt be for the publick good, or elſe it is the abuſe, not the natural Right of Soveraign Power. To which purpoſe he mentions the Opinion of <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Sarisbury,</hi> P. 79. <hi>I do not take away the diſpenſing with the Law out of the Hands of the Powers, but ſuch Precepts or Prohibitions, as have a perpetual Right, are not, as I think, to be ſubjected to their Will and Pleaſure. In thoſe things only that are mutable, the Diſpenſation with the Letter of the Law is to be admitted, yet ſo as by the compenſation of Honeſty or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility the Intention of the Law may be intirely preſerved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that according to this Rule, the natural Inſtances of this diſpenſing Power ſeem to be theſe: When a Law is made, and is for the Publick Good, but happens to fall very ſeverely upon ſome particular Perſons, without their own fault, only becauſe ſuch particular Caſes were not and could not be conſidered in making the Law: here the Equity of the Prince ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive ſuch Sufferers; according to his long Quotation out of <hi>AEneas Sylvius</hi> P. 91. which this Author has tranſcribed at large, and we readily own. When the Penalty annexed to the Law, may in ſome particular caſes be remitted without the publick Injury, and may be thought very juſt and convenient with reſpect to the pittiable Circumſtances, or former Merits of the Perſon offending; as the Archbiſhop obſerves, and this Author from him, P. 79. <hi>While the Laws do ſtand in force, it is fit that ſometimes the King's Clemency ſhould be mingled with the Severity of them; eſpecially when by that means the Subjects may be freed from much detriment and damage.</hi> Which belongs to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51008:11"/> the Regal, not to the Miniſterial Power; <hi>the condition of the Magiſtrates, whoſe Sentence is held corrupt, if it be milder than the Laws, being one thing; the Power of Princes, whom it becometh to qualify the ſharpneſs of them, a far different matter.</hi> If any thing happens after the making of a Law, which was not fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen when it was made, and which is beſides, or contrary to the original intention of the Law-makers, and renders the execution of that Law manifeſtly and notoriouſly oppreſſive to the Publick; the Prince may certainly ſuſpend the Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch Laws, till they be alter'd or repealed by the Power which made them, or in the ſame regular Exerciſe of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power, as they were firſt made. This diſpenſing, and pardoning, ſuſpending Power is ſo neceſſary to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Good, that for my part I would not willingly live under any Government, which wanted the Exerciſe of this Power. And if this be all this Writer intended to prove by his long Quotations out of the <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> I am perfectly of his mind, that the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> was of his Opinion, and ſo, I believe, is every Man who conſiders any thing. For the Exerciſe of ſuch a Power as this, is no Injury to the Laws, nor to the Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Authority. For in this way, the Prime and original In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Law is always ſecure, and can never be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſed with; the general Force and Vigor of the Law is main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, though it be remitted in ſome particular caſes; all Mens Rights and Properties are ſecure, which are ſecured by the Law; (for the Laws can be diſpenſed with, not for the hurt and damage, but only for the Benefit of the Subject, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no legal Rights can be taken away by a Diſpenſation) and more than that, ſome Men may find Refuge and Sanctuary in the Clemency and Soveraign Power of the Prince, from the Severities of the Law, as far as is conſiſtent with the Publick Good and Safety. But any other diſpenſing Power than this, the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> ſays nothing of. And this, I think, is anſwer enough to what he alledges out of Archbiſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After theſe 3 Archbiſhops, the next who follows, is <hi>the humble, patient, and learned Dr.</hi> Robert Sanderſon, <hi>late Lord Biſhop of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51008:11"/> Lincoln;</hi> and were he living, this Writer would exerciſe all the Humility and Patience he had, without offering him any occaſion to ſhew his Learning. At the end of his 9<hi>th</hi> Lecture concerning the final Cauſe of humane Laws, <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. he comes to explain that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſm, <hi>Salus Populi Suprema Lex, The Safety of the People is the Supream Law,</hi> which was expounded in thoſe days, to ſet up the Intereſt and Safety (as they pretended) of the People in oppoſition to the King; which he does with ſo great Learning and Judgment, as not only to confute, but to ſhame all ſuch Protences. From the 18<hi>th Sect.</hi> this Writer, among others, which are nothing to his purpoſe, tranſcribes theſe Words, which I ſuppoſe he thought were: <note place="margin">Non ita ſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luiſſe Legum vinculis aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi.</note> 
               <hi>A King that gives Laws and Statutes to his People, will not (or did not intend) to be bound up by the Laws, that it ſhould not be lawful to him, the Safety of the Common-Wealth being in apparent danger, to provide for the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Kingdom and People committed to him by God, even againſt the Words of the Law. — It is lawful for the Prince in the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his own and his Subjects Safety, to lay aſide for a while all ſtrict obſervance of the Laws, and to make uſe a little of an arbitrary Right, leſt by too unſeaſonable and ſuperſtitious Reverence of the Laws, he may ſuffer both his own Perſon, and his People that are ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to him, and even the Laws themſelves to fall into the Power of his Enemies.</hi> Ergo, the Power of diſpenſing with Penal Laws is an inherent and inſeparable Right of the Crown. <hi>Quod erat demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrandum.</hi> An excellent Logician! to make an accidental Caſe the meaſure and Standard of a conſtant and unalterable Right. To prove that to be a Right when there is no neceſſity, which nothing but Neceſſity can juſtify; nay, to make Neceſſity, which has no Law, the Rule and Pattern of Legal Adminiſtrations; to prove a diſpenſing Power in ordinary caſes from a Right or Neceſſity to act without or againſt Law in extraordinary caſes: For the Biſhop does not here ſay, that in ſuch abſolute Neceſſity the King may diſpenſe with Penal Laws, but that he may act <hi>againſt the Words of the Law, that he may lay aſide for a while</hi> (while that Neceſſity laſts) <hi>all ſtrict obſervance of the Laws, and make uſe of an arbitrary Right.</hi> So that if he can draw any Inference from this to ordinary caſes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51008:12"/> where there is no ſuch abſolute danger, it muſt be to prove a lawleſs and arbitrary Power, which is a great deal more than a Power of diſpenſing with Penal Laws. In the very next Section <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e ſays al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as much of the People; That <hi>it is lawful for Subjects in defence of their Prince and of themſelves (when there is ſuch a preſſing neceſſity, that a pious and prudent Man could not doubt, but if the Lawgiver him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were preſent, he would grant a relaxation of the Law) to have grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter regard to the common Good, which is the ſupream Law, and the end of all Laws, than to any particular Laws, which were made not to prejudice but to ſerve the common Good.</hi> Now ſhould any man hence draw a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Maxim, that all Men muſt have greater regard to the publick Good than to the obſervance of the Laws of their Country, it would be as bad Logick, as it is Divinity and Law.</p>
            <p>The laſt Biſhop he calls in to bear his Teſtimony, is the preſent Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter:</hi> but tho I have ventured to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our dead Biſhops, who cannot ſpeak for themſelves but in their Writings, I dare not make ſo bold with the living: That great Man underſtands his own Senſe beſt, and if he be miſrepreſented, wants neither Learning nor Intereſt to right himſelf.</p>
            <p>And thus we proceed to the Reverend Doctors of our Church, who I believe will be found to ſpeak the ſame things with the moſt Reverend and Right Reverend Biſhops. The firſt is Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> whoſe words are ſaid to be theſe: <hi>He (viz. the King) hath Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by his Prerogative Royal to diſpenſe with the rigor of the Laws, and</hi> ſometimes <hi>to paſs by a Statute with a Non-obſtante.</hi> But where he ſays theſe words, he does not tell us, and therefore I know not where to find them, and therefore know not upon what occaſion they were ſaid, nor to what they are applied. But, as you have already heard, no Man doubts, but in ſome caſes the King may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with the rigor of the Laws, and before the Judges had declared their Opinions in the Point, I know ſome good Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, who did not think, that ſome few Inſtances of a <hi>Non-Obſtante</hi> was a ſufficient proof of a general diſpenſing Power; and why might not Divines be of that mind too? And then the Doctor's ſaying, that the King might <hi>ſometimes</hi> paſs by a Statute with a <hi>Non-obſtante,</hi> does not prove that he was for the diſpenſing
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:51008:12"/> Power in the modern Latitude of it; for though it was as good Law before, as it is now, yet it might not be ſo well underſtood.</p>
            <p>The next in order is the <hi>Learned and Judicious Dr. Iſaac Barrow,</hi> too learned and too judicious to be commended by ſo injudicious a Writer, as will appear from what he tranſcribes out of his Treatiſe concerning the Pope's Supremacy. I was mightily ſurprized to think, what ſhould come into the Doctor's Head to ſtate ſo nice a Point of Law as the diſpenſing Power, in a Treatiſe of the Pope's Supremacy, which ſeem'd as foreign to the buſineſs as could well be imagined; and I was as much afraid that I ſhould not have the Satisfaction of ſeeing what it was, for he was reſolved, if Men would be ſo curious to examine, they ſhould take pains for it; for he directs to no place, where to find what he cites, but ſends his Readers to ſeek for three ſhort Sentences in a Book of 428 Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but by good luck I have found them, and am very much <hi>edified</hi> by them.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Treatiſe of the Supremacy.</hi> P. 311. Quarto.</note> 
               <hi>It is indeed a proper endowment of an abſolute Soveraignty, immediately and immutably conſtituted by God, with no Terms or Rules limiting it, that it's Will declared in way of Precept, Proclamations, concerning the Sanction of Laws, the abrogation of them, the diſpenſation with them ſhould be obſerved.</hi> Where the Doctor was ſhewing how the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> arrogate to themſelves the moſt abſolute and unlimited Soveraignty in the Church, as it follows, <hi>This Priviledg therefore in a high ſtrain the Pope challengeth to himſelf, aſſerting to his Decrees and Sentences the force and obligation of Laws,</hi> &amp;c. The Myſtery of this Quotation is this, that he would have his unwary Readers to believe, that this endowment or priviledg or Prerogative of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power, that it's Will declared in way of Precept, Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, concerning the Sanction of Laws, the abrogation of them, the diſpenſation with them, ſhould be obſerved, is immediately and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutably conſtituted by God, with no terms or rules to limit it: and thus indeed it is home to his purpoſe, but ſhoots vaſtly beyond the Mark: For this does not only prove, that the King may diſpenſe with Laws by his Proclamation, but that he may make and abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Laws too by his Proclamation.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:51008:13"/>
            <p>But the Doctor's plain Senſe is this, That ſuch an abſolute Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty, as is immediately and immutably conſtituted by God, with no terms or rules to limit the exerciſe of it (and ſuch a Soveraignty the Popes have challenged) has this Endowment or Prerogative, that its Will declared in way of Precept, Proclamations, concerning the Sanction of Laws, the abrogation of them, the diſpenſation with them, ſhould be obſerved. And who ever denied this? But I find no one aſſerting, That the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were ſuch abſolute and unlimited Soveraigns, by God's immediate and immutable Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: That their Proclamations were as good Law, as any Acts of Parliament: That they could make and abrogate Laws by their Proclamations. I am ſure Dr. <hi>Barrow</hi> ſaid no ſuch thing, tho our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor did believe, or would have his Readers believe that he did, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he quoted it to no purpoſe. And that is not improbable by his next Quotation, which is to as little purpoſe as one could wiſh. P. 318. <hi>The power of enacting and diſpenſing with Eccleſiaſtical Laws touching exterior Diſcipline, did of old belong to the Emperor</hi> (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not to the Pope, which is the deſign of it) <hi>and it was reaſonable that it ſhould; becauſe old Laws might not conveniently ſute with the preſent ſtate of things, and the publick Welfare; becauſe new Laws might conduce to the good of the Church and State, the care of which is incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on him; becauſe the Prince is bound to uſe his Power and Authority to promote Gods Service, the beſt way of doing which, may be by framing Orders conducible thereto.</hi> And what is all this to a Power of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing with Acts of Parliament, whether they concern Church or State? Who ever, but the Pope, denied the Princes Authority in Eccleſiaſtical Affairs? If the Oath of Supremacy indeed prove the diſpenſing Power; then not only a few Biſhops and Doctors, but the whole Church of <hi>England</hi> teaches it; if it does not, our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor might have ſpared this Quotation.</p>
            <p>And ſo he might his next, P. 400. <hi>It is a Priviledg of Soveraigns to grant Priviledges, Exemptions, and Diſpenſations.</hi> No doubt but it is, and they may in many Caſes do it by Law, which owns this Authority in the Soveraign. There are many legal Priviledges, Exemptions, Diſpenſations, in the Power of the Prince. <hi>Ergo,</hi> What? Thus much for Dr. <hi>Barrow,</hi> and the Pope's Supremacy, which was never favourable to the Prerogatives of Princes. The</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:51008:13"/>
            <p>The next in courſe is <hi>The Reverend Doctor</hi> Sherlock <hi>Master of the Temple, who ſays in a poſitive manner: It does not become any man, who can think three conſequences off, to talk of the Authority of Laws, in derogation of the Authority of the Soveraign Power; The Soveraign Power made the Laws, and can repeal them and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with them, and make new Laws. The only Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Laws is in the Power that can make and execute Laws. Soveraign Power is inſeparable from the Perſon of a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here our Author breaks off, for he durſt go no further, it immediately following: <hi>And though the exerciſe of it may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by Laws, and that Prince does very ill, who, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to ſuch a regulation, breaks the Laws; yet when he acts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, ſuch Acts carry Soveraign and irreſiſtible Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with them, while he continues a Soveraign Prince.</hi> Now it is all out, and let him make his beſt of it.</p>
            <p>But to expoſe the Shuffling Arts of this Writer, it will be conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to conſider what the Dr. was a proving, when theſe words dropt from his Pen. <note place="margin">The Caſe of Nonreſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Supream Powers, <hi>chap.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 186.</note> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at large proved the Doctrine of Non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from Scripture Teſtimonies, and the common Principles of Reaſon, in the Sixth Chapter he anſwers ſome Objections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. The Second Objection is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a Prince has no Authority againſt Law,</hi> as is urged in <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Apoſtate: <hi>There is no Authority on Earth above the</hi> P. 109. <hi>Law, much leſs againſt it. It is murder to put a man to death againſt Law, and if they knew who had Authority to commit open, bare-faced, and down right murders, this would direct them where to pay their Paſſive Obedience: But it would be the horrid'ſt Slander in the World, to ſay that any ſuch Power is lodged in the Prerogative, as to deſtroy Men contrary to Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this the Doctor anſwers, <hi>Now I perfectly agree with them in this alſo, that a Prince has no juſt and legal Authority to act againſt Law; that if he knowingly perſecute any Subject to death contrary to Law, he is a Murderer; and that no Prince has any ſuch Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51008:14"/> to commit open, bare-faced, and down-right Murders. But what follows from hence? Does it hence follow, therefore we may reſiſt and oppoſe them if they do? This I abſolutely deny, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God has expreſly commanded us not to reſist. And I ſee no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency between theſe two Propoſitions, that a Prince has no legal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to perſecute againſt Law, and yet that he muſt not be reſiſted when he does. — He who exceeds the juſt bounds of his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is lyable to be called to an Account for it, but he is account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able only to thoſe who have a Superior Authority to call him to an Account — Thus the Soveraign Prince may exceed his Authority, and is accountable for it to a Superior Power. But becauſe he has no Superior on Earth, he cannot be reſiſted by his own Subjects, but muſt be reſerved to the Judgment of God, who alone is the King of Kings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to what is ſaid, <hi>That an Inauthoritative Act, which carrys no obligation at all, cannot oblige Subjects to Obedience</hi> (thereby meaning Paſſive Obedience) he urges, <hi>That it is very falſe and abſurd, to ſay that every illegal is an Inauthoritative Act, which carrys no obligation with it. This is contrary to the practice of all human Judicatures, and the dayly experience of Men, who ſuffer in their Lives, Bodies, or Eſtates, by an unjuſt and illegal Sentence. Every Judgment, contrary to the true meaning of the Law, is in that ſenſe illegal; and yet ſuch illegal Judgments have their Authority and Obligation, till they are reſcinded by ſome higher Authority:</hi> This he explains at large, and comes at laſt to P. 195. enquire, <hi>Whence an illegal Act or Judgment derives its Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Obligation? The Anſwer is plain; It is from the Authority of the Perſon, whoſe Act or Judgment it is.</hi> Which he proves and confirms in four Propoſitions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That there muſt be a Perſonal Power and Authority antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to all human Laws. For there can be no Laws without a Law-maker; and there can be no Law-maker unleſs there be one or more Perſons invested with the Power of Government, of which making Laws is one branch: For a Law is nothing elſe but the publick and declared will and command of the Law-maker, whether he be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51008:14"/> the Soveraign Prince or the People:</hi> Which ſhows in what ſenſe the Dr. affirmed, <hi>That Soveraign Power made the Laws, and can repeal them, and diſpenſe with them, and make new La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>, viz.</hi> That there is no ſuch thing as a Law without a Lawgiver, who can make, and repeal, and diſpence with Laws, and without whoſe Authority too the Law can have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne. For without doubt the ſame Power that makes Laws can repeal and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpenſe wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h them too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>And hence it neceſſarily follows, That a Soveraign Prince d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> not receive his Authority from the Laws, but Laws receive the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> Authority from him — For the Law has no Authority, nor can give any, but what it receives from the King, and then it is a wonderful Riddle how the King ſhould receive his Authority from the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Hence it foll ws, That the being of Soveraign Power is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent on Laws: That is, As a Soveraign Prince does not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his Power from the Law, ſo, ſhould he violate the Laws by which he is bound to Govern, yet he does not forfeit his Power; H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> breaks his Faith to God and to his Country, but he is a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Prince ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</hi> And in this ſenſe the Dr. affirmed, <hi>That Soveraign Power is inſeparable from the Perſon of a Soveraign Prince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Hence it plainly appears, that every illegal Act the King does is not an Inauthoritative Act, but lays an Obligation on Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to yield, if not an Active yet a Paſſive Obedience. For the King receives not his Soveraign Authority from the Law, nor does he for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>t his Authority by breaking the Law; and therefore he is a Soveraign Prince ſtill, and his moſt illegal Acts, though they have not the Authority of the Law, yet they have the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Soveraign Power, which is irreſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble and unaccountable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this ſhows in what ſenſe the Doctor immediately adds, <hi>It does not become any Man, who can think three conſequences off, to talk of the Authority of Laws in derogation to the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Soveraign Power.</hi> Which does not ſignifie that the Law cannot abridge the Kings diſpenſing Power, nor have the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51008:15"/> Authority of a Rule to him (which he does not meddle with) but that no Law can have ſuch Authority over a Soveraign Prince, as to un-king him, or deprive him of his Soveraign Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and make all his illegal Acts inauthoritative, if he breaks it: For that is the direct anſwer to the Objection; and he ſeems to have looked no further; and indeed to ſpeak the truth, his Argument holds no further; for it does not follow, that the King is not bound to keep the Laws; but he is a King ſtill, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forfeit his Sovereign and irreſiſtable Authority, though he breaks them. But if this Doctors Judgment be of any force, we may learn what his Opinion was, (if he be not now better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed) by his anſwer to the fourth Objection, though poſſibly he will not thank me for my pains in tranſcribing it.</p>
            <p>P. 207. 4. <hi>The next objection againſt the Doctrine of Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, is this, That it deſtroys the difference between an abſolute and limited Monarchy; between a Prince whoſe Will is his Law, and a Prince who is bound to govern by Law: which undermines the Fundamental Conſtitutions of the Engliſh Government.</hi> To this he anſwers, <hi>The difference between an abſolute and limited Monarchy, is not, that Reſiſtance is lawful in one caſe, and unlawful in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, for a Monarch, the exerciſe of whoſe Power is limited and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulated by Laws, is as irreſiſtable as the moſt abſolute Monarch whoſe Will is his Law: and if he were not, I would venture to ſay, that the moſt abſolute and deſpotick Government, is more for the publick good than a limited Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the difference lies in this, that an abſolute Monarch,</hi> (where by <hi>abſolute,</hi> it is plain he means a deſpotick Prince; for otherwiſe, a limited Monarchy may be called, and often is, an abſolute So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereignty,) <hi>is under the Government of no Law, but his own Will: He can make and repeal Laws at his pleaſure, without asking the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of any of his Subjects: he can impoſe what Taxes he pleaſes, and is not tied up to ſtrict Rules and Formalities of Law in the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Justice. But it is quite contrary in a limited Monarchy; where the exerciſe of the Soveraign Power is regulated by known and ſtanding Laws, which the Prince can neither make nor repeal without
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51008:15"/> the conſent of the People,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>No, you will ſay, the caſe is juſt the ſame. For what do Laws ſignifie, when a Prince muſt not be reſiſted, though he break theſe Laws, and govern by an arbitrary and lawleſs Will? He may make himſelf as abſolute as the Great</hi> Turk <hi>or the</hi> Mogul, <hi>when ever he pleaſes: For what ſhould hinder him, when all mens hands are tied by this Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance? now it muſt be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that there is a poſſibility for ſuch a Prince to govern arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, and to trample upon all Laws: And yet the difference between an abſolute and limited Monarchy, is vastly great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For this Prince, though he may make his Will a Law to himſelf, and the only Rule of his Government, yet he cannot make it the Law of the Land. He may break Laws, but he cannot make nor repeal them: and therefore he can never alter the Frame and Conſtitution of the Government; though he may at preſent interrupt the regular adminiſtration of it: And this is a great ſecurity to Poſterity, and a preſent reſtraint upon himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>For it is a mighty uneaſie thing to any Prince, to govern con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to known Laws: He offers as great and conſtant violence to himſelf, as he does to his Subjects. — The breach of his Oath to God, and his promiſes and engagements to his Subjects, makes the exerciſe of ſuch an arbitrary Power very troubleſom. And though his Subjects are bound not to reſiſt him, yet his own guilty fears will not ſuffer him to be ſecure: And arbitrary Power is not ſo luſcious a thing, as to tempt Men to forfeit all the eaſe and pleaſure and ſecurity of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the ſake of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Though Subjects muſt not reſiſt ſuch a Prince, who violates the Laws of his Kingdom; yet they are not bound to obey him, and ſerve him in his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations. — Subjects are bound to yield an active obedience only according to Law, though they are bound not to reſiſt when they ſuffer againſt Law. Now it is a mighty uneaſy thing to the greateſt Tyrant, to govern always by force. And no Prince in a limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Monarchy can make himſelf abſolute, unleſs his own Subjects aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him to do ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>And yet it is very dangerous for any Subject to ſerve his Prince contrary to Law; though the Prince himſelf is unaccountable and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51008:16"/> irreſistible, yet his Miniſters may be called to an account, and be puniſht for it; and the Prince may think fit, to look on qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>tly and ſee it done: or if they eſcape at pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent, it may be time enough to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for it under the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ext Prince which we ſee by experience makes all Men wary how they ſerve their Prince againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>aw: None but Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of deſperate Fortunes will do this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ated; and theſe are not always to be met with, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eldom fit to be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>And therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> may obſerve, that by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undamental Laws of our Government, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> govern <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>; ſo he is irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhews, that our wiſe Law-makers d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t think that Non reſiſtance was deſtructive of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ited M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not long ſince this was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>gh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and I am ſure it is very neceſſary to keep Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>Prince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; for which reaſon I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> though it doth not reach the height <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And now I find our Author begins to run <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes up with Doctor <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſon,</hi> who ſays, <hi>In the Kings Power it is to remit the ſeverities of the penal Laws, whereby he may m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>st his clemency and goodneſs, as well as his greatneſs and juſtice, of graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pardoning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>maller Breaches of his Laws, and the more ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital offences, which he might moſt justly puniſh:</hi> For whoever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied this? The King, without doubt, may not only pardon ſome ſmaller Fault, but the greateſt of Crimes: but how this is to his purpoſe, I ſtill want to be inform'd.</p>
            <p>And ſo I do, as to what he quotes out of Doctor <hi>Puller</hi>'s Book, concerning <hi>The Moderation of the Church of</hi> England. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Equity which conſiſts <hi>in remitting of the rig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> of the Laws, when they preſs too hard upon particular Perſons; or in ſupplying the defects of the ſaid Laws, where they provide not ſufficiently for particular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſes,</hi> which is all Doctor <hi>Puller</hi> contends for, be all that this Writer wou'd have, what need he to have writ a book about it, and confirm'd it with ſo many great Authorities; when I don't know, that in this he has an Adverſary in the World; if he have, it is fit ſuch a man, if ever he ſtood in need of Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Mercy, ſhou'd never have it. Who thinks the Court of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:51008:16"/> Chancery, an illegal Court? and yet that is properly a Court of Equity. It is one thing to moderate the rigour of Laws in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable caſes; another to diſpenſe univerſally with ſuch Laws, as, if Doctor <hi>Puller</hi>'s Book prove any thing, are very moderate already; and yet this may be the Prince's Prerogative, reſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting not from Moderation and Equity, but a Plenitude of Power.</p>
            <p>As for his Anonymous Author, with whom he concludes, I neither know him nor his Book, and ſuppoſe the cauſe will not depend upon a ſingle Authority.</p>
            <p>Thus we have heard what <hi>the Reverend Prelates and Doctors of the Church of</hi> England <hi>have ſaid of this matter: in the next place, he tells us what were the Reaſons that induc'd the Reverend Judges in</hi> Weſtminſter-Hall <hi>ſo openly and ſolemnly, after mature deliberation, to declare their Reſolutions in this Point for the thing.</hi> But I had much rather he had told us what their Reſolution was, how far they extended this diſpenſing Power; whether to all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or only to ſome, or to all, or to ſome as the King at any time judges neceſſary; for I have heard very different Accounts of the matter, but cou'd never ſee any authentick Record of it: To have inform'd us in this matter, had been a real Kindneſs, becauſe 'tis the Rule of our Actions, of our Words, and of our Writing too: for when I once know what the <hi>Judges</hi> declare to be Law, I will enquire no further; their Opinions ſolemnly declar'd, muſt ſilence all Diſputes, becauſe they carry Power and Authority with them, unleſs any ſuperiour Authority think fit at any time to judge over their Opinions.</p>
            <p>This makes it very neceſſary to know what the Judgment and Reſolution of the <hi>Judges</hi> is, eſpecially in any great and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Points; but as for their Reaſons I am not ſo fond of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, becauſe it is the Authority of the Men, not of their Reaſons, which muſt determine ſuch matters: for Mankind rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning ſo very differently as they do, there never cou'd be any final Determination of ſuch Caſes, if all men muſt be firſt ſatisfied in the validity of their Reaſons: And therefore I think this Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51008:17"/> has done no ſervice to the Cauſe, by making their Reaſons the Subject of Diſpute; for tho' they may be very good Reaſons, yet it may be, all men will not think ſo; and then ſuch men will be apt to be diſſatisfied, that a Judgment (which as they think) is not founded on ſufficient Reaſons, ſhou'd have ſuch great Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p>For it is not enough to ſay as this Writer does, <hi>That the Reaſons they went upon, were only ſuch as were exactly correſpondent with the avow'd Doctrines before recited; and that by this Declaration of theirs, the Law of the Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>concerning this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Power in the Crown, is no more than what was before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly aſſerted to be the Divinity of the Kindom.</hi> For tho' the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of the Kingdom</hi> is a great word, and cannot be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by a Jury of <hi>Divines,</hi> who liv'd in different Ages, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpoke together about it; nay, indeed can never be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd by any ſingle <hi>Divines,</hi> tho' never ſo many, and never ſo learned, but only by the Authority of a <hi>Convocation,</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Synod;</hi> yet thoſe who think the Reaſons not good, will like them never the better, becauſe ſome <hi>Divines</hi> have been of that mind, when they can ſo out number (as I ſaid before) the Church of <hi>England</hi> with Popiſh and Fanatick Divines, who teach another Doctrine. And beſides this, I doubt he puts it upon a very dangerous Iſſue. For, if after all his confidence and aſſurance, other men ſhou'd not think that theſe Reaſons do ſo exactly correſpond with the avow'd Doctrines of the Biſhops and Doctors of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that they have neither taught the ſame Doctrine, nor us'd the ſame Reaſons, (as poſſibly this Author by that time he has read thus far, may ſee reaſon to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect) what then! had he not better have let all this alone? have not the <hi>Reverend Judges</hi> great reaſon to thank him for bringing their Judgment and Reaſons to ſuch a Teſt, as they will not bear? They need not the Authority of <hi>Divines</hi> to juſtifie their Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations at Law; and therefore it is, at beſt, over-officiouſneſs, and a leſſening of their Authority, to make ſuch Appeals, beſides the folly and raſhneſs of making ſuch Appeals as will do no Service.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51008:17"/>
            <p>But ſuppoſe theſe were not the <hi>Judges</hi> Reaſons, how will he juſtifie himſelf for publiſhing theſe Reaſons as theirs, without their Authority? which I dare boldly ſay, he never had. Nay, I dare lay conſiderable odds, that theſe were not their Reaſons, as he has worded and repreſented them, and that for more Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons than one: Did all the <hi>Judges</hi> agree upon theſe Reaſons, and make a Record of them? or has he ſeen them ſigned with all their Hands? if not, how does he know that theſe are their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons? For a Bench of Judges may agree in their Concluſion, when they differ in their Premiſes and Reaſons: And I will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they had other Reaſons beſides theſe here mentioned. Poſſibly ſome ſuch thing as this might be ſaid in Court, but I believe, not as it is here reported; and it is an Affront to <hi>Judges</hi> in ſuch a weighty Point as this, to declare their Reaſons upon meer hear-ſay; when it is ſo evident, that of twenty men, who hear the ſame thing, ſearce two of them ſhall exactly agree in their Report; ſo uncertain and variable a thing is Oral Tradition, which how infallible ſoever it may be in Divinity, is not ſo in Law.</p>
            <p>But to let all this paſs, and to allow theſe Reaſons to be very good; for I will no more diſpute any Reaſons, which are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the <hi>Judges,</hi> than I will diſpute their Reſolutions; yet the queſtion ſtill remains, Whether theſe Reaſons are exactly the ſame with what the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have formerly taught? This he aſſerts, and this, I hope, I may exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine without any offence; for it is no Condemnation of their Reaſons, tho' I ſhou'd ſay, that they were never us'd by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines. Now a Reaſon has a neceſſary Relation to the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or to that which is to be prov'd by it; for tho' a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men ſhould ſay the ſame thing, and draw a hundred ſeveral Concluſions from it, you cannot ſay, that their Reaſon is the ſame, becauſe their Concluſions are not the ſame; for thoſe only reaſon alike, who from the ſame Premiſes draw the ſame Concluſion: ſo that tho' every one of theſe Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are here ſaid to be the <hi>Judges</hi> Reaſons, had been
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51008:18"/> aſſerted a hundred times over by the <hi>Divines</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> yet if they did not draw the ſame Concluſion from them, which the <hi>Reverend Judges</hi> have done, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaid to be the ſame Reaſons; and whether they have done that, or not, may be learn'd from what has been already ſaid.</p>
            <p>And yet in truth, I cannot tell whether the Premiſes be the ſame or not; for they are ſet down in ſuch looſe, and general terms in this Paper, as admit of very different Senſes; and in which Senſe they are underſtood by the <hi>Reverend Judges,</hi> is not ſaid. And therefore I ſhall ſhew you in what Senſe theſe Propoſitions have been own'd by the Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then thoſe who know the <hi>Judges</hi> ſenſe of them, will eaſily ſee where they agree, and where they differ.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the Kings of</hi> England <hi>are Soveraign Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is univerſally own'd by the Divines of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> but then they make ſome difference between Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Princes, not with reſpect to the fulneſs of Power, for they have all the Rights of Soveraignty, but with reſpect to the Exerciſe of this Soveraign Power: for ſome Princes are under no Reſtraints and Limitations, but only the Laws of God and Nature: they can make what Laws they pleaſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal them when they pleaſe, diſpenſe with them as they pleaſe, without the conſent of any but themſelves: Other Soveraign Princes, tho' they have all Soveraign Power, and therefore are irreſiſtable and unaccountable to any but God; yet the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Power is by their own conſent directed and regulated by Laws, that they can neither make, nor abrogate Laws, but by the Conſent of their Nobles and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and therefore tho' they never can do any thing to forfeit their Power, yet they may do that, which is illegal; and how far the legal Exerciſe of ſuch a Soveraign Power extends, muſt be known by the particular Laws and Conſtitutions of their ſeveral Kingdoms, not from the unlimited
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51008:18"/> notions of Soveraign Power, and Soveraign Will and Pleaſure: And the Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have generally look'd upon the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> as ſuch a limitted Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy; and if they have been miſtaken in it, I hope it is a pardonable miſtake, becauſe it has been ſo general.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the Laws of</hi> England <hi>are the Kings Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo is univerſally acknowledged, and the reaſon aſſigned for it by the Learned Doctor <hi>Sanderſon;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sanderſ.</hi> Praelectio ſeptima de Legum humanarum cauſâ effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente. Quin &amp; in jure noſtro, &amp; in quotidianis proceſſibus ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridicis in foro contentioſo ex <hi>ſolenni</hi> formulâ <hi>Regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Leges</hi> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> ſolent <hi>(the King's Laws)</hi> non aliam ob cauſam, ut nos docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erunt juris noſtri periti, quam quod <hi>Reges Angliae ſint fons ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; Legum:</hi> &amp; legibus ipſis <hi>ut pro legibus habeantur</hi> vim om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem imponendi habeant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſam ſibi à Deo <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, poteſtatem.</note> becauſe, as the Lawyers teach, the Kings of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> are the Fountain of Juſtice and Laws, and have alone that Soveraign Authority, that can give the Force and Vertue of Laws to the Laws them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. For tho', as he obſerves, there is ſomething neceſſary to prepare the matter for Laws, as the conſent and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Parliament, yet it is the conſent of the King only, which gives them the Form and Obligation of Laws: So that they are the Kings Laws, becauſe that it is his Authority that makes them Laws; but when they are made Laws by the King, they become the Laws of the Land, the Rule of his own Government, and his Subjects Obedience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That</hi> therefore <hi>it is an incident inſeparable Prerogative in the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>as in all other Soveraign Princes, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with penal Laws in particular caſes, and upon particular ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Reaſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is alſo aſſerted by the Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> That the King may pardon what Crimes he pleaſes, and in ſome caſes, upon great and urgent neceſſities, may diſpence with ſome Laws for a greater publick Good, or for the Relief of ſome particular Perſons, where the Law appears too hard and rigorous, while the general Intention and Vigour of the Law is ſecur'd: For as they urge, the Imperfection of all humane Laws requires ſuch an Authority as this to ſupply their defects.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51008:19"/> But <hi>the therefore</hi> I do not ſo well underſtand, for I find none of them reſolve this diſpenſing Power into the Laws, being the Kings Laws, which indeed will prove a Power of diſpenſing with all Laws where he pleaſes; for all Laws, as well as penal Laws, are the Kings Laws. Nor do I find any of them ſay, that this diſpenſing Power is equal in all Soveraign Princes. For they generally make ſome difference between abſolute and limited Soveraigns; that is, the Exerciſe of whoſe Power is bounded by Laws of their own making: the firſt ſort, who can make and abrogate Laws at their own pleaſure, may certainly diſpenſe with them alſo, when they ſee fit; whether thoſe, who can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make nor abrogate Laws, without the conſent of their People, can diſpence with what Laws they pleaſe, is a queſtion, which I find no where debated among them, and therefore cannot give their opinion in it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That of theſe Reaſons and theſe Neceſſities the King himſelf is Sole Judge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I do not find any of our Divines meddle with, tho' I think the Caſe is very plain; every Man judges for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and will do ſo; and therefore a Soveraign Prince, who has no Superiour, will finally judge for himſelf, and no man can call him to an account for it, no more than they can reſiſt him, tho' he ſhou'd judge amiſs, and exerciſe an illegal Power: But this does not alter the caſe, nor make that le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal, which in it ſelf is illegal; he is concern'd to judge right, and exerciſe no Authority, but what he may, becauſe there is a Superiour Judge even of Soveraign Princes; and then, which is conſequent upon all.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That this is not a truſt, vested in, or granted to the King by the People, but is the ancient remains of the Soveraign Power, and Prerogatives of the Kings of</hi> England, <hi>which never yet was taken from them, nor can be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo is univerſally own'd by the Divines of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> receive no power or Authority from the People; for all Soveraign Power comes
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51008:19"/> from God, and the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> is not Elective but Hereditary: Nay, they own, that no Eſſential branch of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Power, can be taken away from a Soveraign Prince: the only queſtion is, whether the exerciſe of Soveraign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, can be regulated and limited by Laws of the Kings own making? and this thoſe who talk of a limited Monarchy, muſt own: for there can be no limited Monarchy, if the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Soveraign Power cannot be bounded by Laws. Thus I have ſhewn, as well as I can learn, what the Senſe of the <hi>Divines</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is in theſe Points; how far they agree with the <hi>Judges</hi> reaſons, if they be theirs, I cannot tell, becauſe I know not in what Senſe they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them.</p>
            <p>As for his application of all this, to the caſe of <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> I have nothing at all to ſay to it: for ſince the King has declar'd his pleaſure in it, I will not diſpute againſt it: I am not without hope, that <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> will not do the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſo much hurt, as her Adverſaries wiſh, nor the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo much good as they expected: for tho' Fanaticiſm is a pleaſing deluſion, Popery is not popular in this age; and therefore it is not meer ſhowing, that will make Converts; and I believe <hi>Liberty of Conſcience</hi> it ſelf, at this time, will not drive any Sober Diſſenter the farther from Church.</p>
            <p>And I have more hope of Gods Protection, becauſe we are upbraided, as we are by this Writer, with our very hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the Divine Providence; for who ever reads it, can think it nothing leſs, beſides the knavery of the Quotation.</p>
            <p>Doctor <hi>Hicks,</hi> in anſwer to that Objection againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Paſſive Obedience, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jovian</hi> p. 263.</note> 
               <hi>Where then is our ſecurity? How can we be ſafe from the oppreſſion of our Soveraign, if we may not be allow'd to reſiſt?</hi> Among other things tells his Readers, <note place="margin">Pag. 265.</note> that <hi>there neither is, nor can be any abſolute ſecurity, either for the Soveraign againſt the Subjects, or for the Subjects againſt the Soveraign, in any Government: and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51008:20"/> therefore in the ſecond place, it may be a ſufficient anſwer to the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, to ſhow, that we have all the ſecurity againſt the King, that the King hath againſt us; even all the ſecurity, that any people in the World ever had, have or ought to have; and he instances in the Providence of God, in the Conſcience, and Honour of the King, and in the Laws of the Realm, to which every man, be he never ſo great, is obnoxious, beſides the Prince himſelf.</hi> This was all ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to the Doctors purpoſe, it being all the Security we can have, that our Prince will not oppreſs us, which is not abſolute ſecurity neither. But what does this ſignifie to Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? how does this ſecure the Church of <hi>England</hi> if all her Enemies be let looſe upon her?</p>
            <p>But this Writer picking out two or three ſayings from what the Doctor ſaid of the Divine Providence, without any regard to the <hi>ſeries</hi> of the Argument, concludes it with theſe words in Capital Letters. <hi>So that they have all the ſecurity that any People in the world ever had, have, or ought to have.</hi> As if the Doctor had taught, that no People in the World ever had, or ought to have, any other ſecurity againſt the Oppreſſion of a Soveraign Prince, but only the Providence and Protection of God; whereas he applies this not only to the Providence of God, but <hi>To the Conſcience and Honour of the King, and the ſecurity of Laws:</hi> The Providence of God indeed has the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling determination of all things, but ordinary Providence works by means, and we have no reaſon to expect Miracles now; and therefore the Providence of God does not make o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſecurities needleſs.</p>
            <p>The Doctor tells us, <note place="margin">Page 267.</note> 
               <hi>As the Princes beſt ſecurity against the People, is the watchful Providence of God; ſo the ſame watchful Providence is the Peoples beſt ſecurity againſt the Prince:</hi> So that the Providence of God is an equal ſecurity to Prince and People againſt each other: But how would any Prince look upon ſuch a trifler, who ſhould tell him, Sir, all the ſecurity you have, or poſſibly can have againſt your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, is only the Providence and Protection of God, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51008:20"/> therefore you may ſave Money, and disband your Guards and Armies. To perſwade Men to part with all other ſecurities, and to venture upon the moſt deſtructive Methods, in confidence of the divine Protection, is like the Devils Temptation to Chriſt, to caſt himſelf down from the Pinnacle of the Temple; for it is written, <hi>he ſhall give his Angels charge concerning thee, and in their hands they ſhall bear thee up, leſt at any time thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone,</hi> 4. Mat. 6. I believe both Prince and People de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire all the ſecurity they can, and do not think it reaſonable to part with one good ſecurity, becauſe they have another. We have the Kings Word, his Conſcience, his Honour, and his Laws, and thank God for all, and implore the Protection of his Providence, without which all other Securities are nothing; and next to the Providence of God, Laws are the beſt ſecurity, becauſe they are the Foundation of Conſcience and Honour too, and of all promiſes to govern by Laws; for Conſcience reſpects Laws, and where there is no Law in the the caſe, Conſcience is not concern'd and can hinder nothing; and to be ſure the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a Prince, as well as Conſcience, is leſs concern'd, when it is under no reſtraint of Laws.</p>
            <p>He concludes this Pamphlet with ſome few Authorities for Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of Conſcience; I ſhall not now examine how pertinent they are, for I will give no other Anſwer but this; when he has an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered all the Presbyterian Arguments againſt Toleration, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that Book call'd <hi>Tolleration diſcus'd,</hi> and the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Doctor <hi>Parker,</hi> now the Right Reverend Biſhop of <hi>Oxford</hi> in his Eccleſiaſtical Policy: When he can prove, that Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Conſcience is the Doctrine and Practiſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the ſtanding Rule of the Inquiſition, then I will conſider further on this Argument. In the mean time, Sir I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:51008:21"/>
            <head>Books lately printed for <hi>Richard Chiſwell.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Neceſſity of Reformation, with reſpect to the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Corruptions of the <hi>Church of Rome. Quarto.</hi> Firſt and Second Parts.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Celebration of Divine Service in an Unknown Tongue. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Papiſt not Miſrepreſented by Proteſtants. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Expoſition of the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> in the ſeveral Articles propoſed by the late BISHOP of <hi>CONDOM,</hi> [in his Expoſition of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>] <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Expoſition</hi> of the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of ENGLAND,</hi> againſt the <hi>EXCEPTIONS</hi> of <hi>Monſieur de MEA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Condom,</hi> and his <hi>VINDICATOR. Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An Anſwer to <hi>THREE PAPERS</hi> lately printed, concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> in Matters of Faith, and the Reformation of the <hi>Church of England. Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Vindication of the Anſwer to SOME LATE PAPERS concerning the Unity and Authority of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and Reformation of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Quarto.</item>
               <item>An Hiſtorical Treatiſe written by an AUTHOR of the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of ROME,</hi> touching <hi>TRANS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BSTANTIATION.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is made appear, That according to the Principles of <hi>THAT CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH,</hi> This Doctrine cannot be an Article of Faith. <hi>Quarto</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>CATECHISM</hi> explaining the Doctrine and Practices of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> with an Anſwer thereunto. By a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> 8vo.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Law-Chriſtian</hi>'s Obligations to read the Holy Scriptures. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Plain Man</hi>'s Reply to the <hi>Catholick Miſſionaries.</hi> 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>The Proteſtant's Companion: Or an Impartial Survey, and Compariſon of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> as by Law eſtabliſhed, with the main <hi>Doctrines of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery.</hi> Wherein is ſhewn, that Popery is contrary to Scripture. Primitive Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Councils; and that proved from Holy Writ, the Writings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Ancient Fathers, for ſeveral hundred Years, and the Confeſſion of the moſt Learned Papiſts themſelves. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe of the <hi>Holy Euchariſt,</hi> in the two great points of the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> and the <hi>Adoration of the Hoſt.</hi> In Anſwer to the Two Diſcourſes lately printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> on this Subject. To which is prefixed a large Hiſtorical Preface rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the ſame Argument. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Pillar and Ground of Truth. A Treatiſe ſhewing that the <hi>Roman Church</hi> falſly claims to be <hi>That Church,</hi> and the Pillar of <hi>That Truth,</hi> mentioned by S. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy, Chap.</hi> III <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Brief Diſcourſe concerning the Notes of the Church, with ſome reflections on Cardinal <hi>Bell rmin</hi>'s Fifteen Notes. <hi>Quarto.</hi> whereof Ten are extant. The reſt will be Publiſhed in their order.</item>
               <item>A Defence of the Confuter of <hi>Bellarmin</hi>'s Second Note of the Church [<hi>Antiquity</hi>] againſt the Cavills of the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>viſer. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Peoples Right to read the Holy Scriptures aſſerted. In Anſwer to the <hi>6th, 7th, 8th, 9th</hi> and <hi>10th</hi> Chapters of the [<hi>Popiſh Repreſenter,</hi> Second Part].</item>
               <item>Two Diſcourſes: Of Purgatory and Prayers for the Dead. <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Short Summ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry of the Principal Controverſies between the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> Being a Vindication of ſeveral Proteſtant Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, in Anſwer to a late Pamphlet intituled [<hi>Proteſtancy deſtitute of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-Proofs</hi>].</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
